Hannah Moshontz de la Rocha, PhD

LinkedIn | academic cv | google scholar | www.hannahmoshontz.com

Summary

Behavioral and cognitive scientist with 10+ years of experience conducting transparent, rigorous research. Strong methodological and quantitative skills. Successfully managed and completed numerous complex, highly collaborative projects during doctoral training, postdoctoral training, and time as an industry data scientist.

EDUCATION

PhD and MA, Duke University

Department of Psychology and Neuroscience

BA, Reed College

Portland, OR

Durham, NC

Department of Psychology

2011

2020

Positions

Data Scientist

April 2022 - present

Hunt Club

Chicago, IL

- Designed measures and identified and calculated metrics from data that answered meaningful business questions about user experience for the Product team
- Worked with cross-functional teams and leadership to identify data errors and improve error-correction processes
- Created company-wide data documentation and data standards for platform data and analytics warehouse
- Led and managed an analytics engineer in setting up a BigQuery warehouse and BI tooling in Looker

Postdoctoral Researcher and NIH T32 Fellow

June 2020 - March 2022

PI: John Curtin, University of Wisconsin - Madison

Madison. WI

- Coordinated and managed a NIH R01-funded study to build machine learning models for lapses among people recovering from Opioid Use Disorder
- Led a team of two full-time staff and three graduate-student assistants, collaborated with a technical team of app developers, and successfully followed direction set by co-PIs in different departments with complementary content expertise

Doctoral Student August 2014 – May 2020

PI: Rick Hoyle, Duke University

Durham, NC

- Designed, conducted, and analyzed dozens of observational and experimental research studies
- Mentored two undergraduate thesis projects and served as an individual or collaborative mentor to five independent study students
- Taught a Research Methods course as the instructor of record and served as the TA for 5 courses, including both of the Psychology and Neuroscience Department's graduate-level statistics courses
- Earned numerous grants, honors, and fellowships including from the Duke Program for Advanced Research in the Social Sciences, the Duke Education Human Development Program, the Summer Institute for Personality and Social Psychology, and honorable mention for the NSF GRFP

Relevant skills

Data and statistics: SQL, R, SAS, Python, HTCondor, Mplus

Research workflows: OSF, preregistration, data documentation, Rmd and Quarto

Statistical Analysis: Generalized linear models (GLM) inclusive of multi-level modeling and structural equation modeling, GLM-based machine learning methods, cross-validation and related resampling methods

- Legate, N., Nguyen, T. T., Weinstein, N., Moller, A. C., Legault, L., ... Moshontz, H., ... Primbs, M. (2022). A Global Experiment on Motivating Social Distancing during the COVID-19 Pandemic. *The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*. doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2111091119 Preprint
- Nosek, B. A., Hardwicke, T. E., **Moshontz, H.**, Allard, A., Corker, K. S., Dreber, A., Fidler, F., Hilgard, J., Kline Struhl, M., Nuijten, M., Rohrer, J., Romerio, F., Scheel, A., Scherer, L., Schonbrodt, F., & Vazire, S. (2022). Replicability, Robustness, and Reproducibility in Psychological Science. *Annual Review of Psychology*, 73(1). doi.org/10.1146/annurev-psych-020821-114157 Preprint
- Moshontz, H., Colmenares, A., Fronk, G.E., Sant'Ana, S.J., Paquette, K., Wyant, S.E., Maus, A., Gustafson, D.H., Shah, D.V., & Curtin, J.J. (2021). Prospective Prediction of Lapses in Opioid Use Disorder: Protocol for a Personal Sensing Study. *JMIR Research Protocols*. doi.org/10.2196/29563 Preprint
- Wang, K., Goldenberg, A., Dorison, C.A., Miller, J.K., Uusberg, A., Lerner, J.S., Gross, J.J., ... **Moshontz, H.** (2021) A multi-country test of brief reappraisal interventions on emotions during the COVID-19 pandemic. *Nature Human Behavior*. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01173-x Preprint
- Moshontz, H., Binion, G. E., Walton, H., M. Syed, & Brown, B. T. (2021). A Guide to Posting and Managing Preprints. *Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science*, 4(2), 1-11. doi.org/10.1177/25152459211019948 Preprint
- *Moshontz, H., *Ebersole, C.R., Weston, S.J., & Klien, R.A. (2021). A Guide for Many Authors: Writing Manuscripts in Large Collaborations. *Social and Personality Psychology Compass*, 15(4), e12590. doi.org/10.1111/spc3.12590 Preprint
- Moshontz, H. & Hoyle, R.H. (2021). Resisting, Recognizing, and Returning: A Three-Component Model and Review of Persistence in Episodic Goals. *Social and Personality Psychology Compass* 15(1), e12576. doi.org/10.1111/spc3.12576 Preprint
- *McAuliffe, W.H., *Moshontz, H., McCauley, T.G., & McCullough, M.E. (2020). Searching for Prosociality in Qualitative Data: Comparing Manual, Closed–Vocabulary, and Open–Vocabulary Methods. *European Journal of Personality* 34, 903-916. doi.org/10.1002/per.2240 Preprint
- Powers, J.P., **Moshontz, H.**, & Hoyle, R.H. (2020). Self-Control and Affect Regulation Styles Predict Anxiety Longitudinally in University Students. *Collabra: Psychology* 6(1), 11. doi.org/10.1525/collabra.280 Preprint
- Crüwell, S., van Doorn, J., Etz, A., Makel, M., **Moshontz, H.**, Niebaum, J., . . . Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M. (2019). Seven Easy Steps to Open Science: An Annotated Reading List. *Zeitschrift für Psychologie*. doi.org/10.1027/2151-2604/a000387 Preprint
- Moshontz, H., Campbell, L., Ebersole, C.R., IJzerman, H., Urry, H.L., Forscher, P.S., ... Chartier, C.R. (2018). The Psychological Science Accelerator: Advancing Psychology Through a Distributed Collaborative Network. Advances in Methods and Practices in Psychological Science, 1(4), 501–515 doi.org/10.1177/2515245918797607 Preprint
- Atkinson, K.M., Koenka, A.C., Sanchez, C.E., **Moshontz, H.** & Cooper, H.M. (2015). Reporting Standards for Literature Searches and Report Inclusion: Making Research Syntheses More Transparent and Easy to Replicate. *Research Synthesis Methods*, 6(1), 87-95. doi.org/10.1002/jrsm.1127